בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is מג *mem gimmel* and
we are getting into, you know, we are now to very practical
discussions about things that are not full חמץ chametz. *chametz* but are
still forbidden. And we had the list in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
of two categories of things. First list of things that were certainly
foods, but they were not loaves of bread or cookies or crackers,
they were תערובת חמץ taarovas chometz, *tarovet chametz*, they were some mixture.
You had one thing which actually used moldy bread in some type
of a milk-based or sour milk-based mixture like כותח kutach. *kutach*, and
you had other things that did, that put barley
into
wine in order to make vinegar, or barley into some type of
a mead in order to make beer. And there, you know, it
never even started as bread, but you definitely
had liquid and flour or liquid and grain coming together. But again,
it was in a larger mixture of something else. So that was
חמץ בתערובת chometz betaarovas, *chametz betarovet*.
Then the last set of the cases in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
were various types of,
what's the word, not medicine, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* calls it
מיני אומנות *minei umanut*, materials used in a professional context where it
might have had a חמץ chametz. *chametz* content or might have even
been all חמץ chametz, *chametz*, but it was not really edible and
it wasn't made for that purpose. So you have things that like,
you know, things that were made for glue or things that were
made for some type of a plaster to put on the skin
to peel off hairs, these types of things which might have been
a major, you know, flour-based content, but nevertheless, it was not made
for eating and presumably not even fully edible. So there was those
two categories of things: תערובת חמץ taarovas chometz. *tarovet chametz* and a
category that we're going to see in a minute is going to
be called חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha, *chametz nuksha*, which is non-fully fermented
or non-fully edible חמץ chametz *chametz*, which is primarily made for non-food
purposes. And both of those, there is a negative prohibition for eating
it, but there is not כרת kareth, *karet*. And we're going to
have to see today how where do we get this idea that
there's this middle category of enough חמץ chametz, *chametz* to be forbidden
but not enough to get כרת kares, *karet*, talking about creating a
hierarchy. And as I also mentioned the other day, there's a debate
in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* whether this type of middle category you
transgress the biblical prohibition of בל יראה בל ימצא *bal yera'eh bal
yimatze* of owning. Certainly rabbinically you're not allowed to own, but there's
a debate whether biblically as well. But anyway, those were the two
categories: foods that had a mixture of חמץ chametz *chametz* and non-foods
that were used in professional purposes, didn't really and were not really
necessarily edible. So let's take a look now. We pick up two
lines from the bottom on מב עמוד ב bet, *mem bet amud
bet* with the last line in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* about רבי
אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* who includes one final category. רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer אומר אף תכשיטי נשים nashim *Rabbi Eliezer omer af takhshitei
nashim*, even women's jewelry is literally what it means. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says תכשיטי נשים סלקא דעתך *takhshitei nashim salka datakh*, what,
women's jewelry? How is that חמץ chametz. *chametz*? אלא אימא eima, אף
טיפולי נשים *ela eima af tipulei nashim*, means women's cosmetics, דאמר רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר רב Rav אמר רב Rav, בנות ישראל שהגיעו
לפירקן ולא הגיעו לשנים *de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar Rav Bnos
Yisrael shehigi'u lepirkan velo higi'u leshanim*, if you have young Jewish girls
that have reached maturity, right, שהגיעו לפירקן *shehigi'u lepirkan*, they've, so they're
physically mature, correct, but they are not yet of the right age
where that's expected yet. So therefore, they're exhibiting, now the concern here
seems to be specifically that they're exhibiting hair that does not seem
that is not seen as appropriate. Of course, the hair presumably is
pubic hair and it's not exactly clear who's looking at it unless,
of course, you're talking about, you know, these girls that are married,
underage girls that are married, which we know is also a phenomenon.
So that's the phenomenon, that they are physically mature but they're not
yet of the right age. So what would they do? בנות עניים
טופלות אותן בסיד *Bnos aniyim toplos otan besid*, so the poor ones,
you know, obviously it's also interesting, you know, that again, sort of
reflecting the patriarchal nature of the society. It doesn't say poor girls,
it says daughters of poor people, meaning of poor men, right? So
again, it's all in reference to the men. Okay, so the poor
ones would, would sort of use a plaster that they would apply
to their skin and then peel off the hairs. בנות עשירים טופלות
אותן בסולת *Bnos ashirim toplos otan besoles*, rich ones would apply a
type of a dough-based סולת *soles* spread that they would peel off.
Dough is more expensive than plaster. And again, there by the way,
you have this idea that it's a dough-based cosmetic, you know, cosmetic
thing. Depilatory. Depilatory, yes.
ובנות
מלכים שמן המור *Uvnos melachim shemen hamor*, and the daughters of kings,
you know, the super rich would use שמן המור *shemen hamor*, would
use a type of an oil that would make it fall off,
שנאמר shene'emar, ששה חדשים בשמן המור וששה חדשים בבשמים *shenemar shisha chodashim
beshemen hamor veshisha chodashim babesamim*. We know that Esther did it. Right.
And so therefore, so presumably, I don't know how we know that
just because Esther did it, it meant that it was done for
that purpose, but that's what we say is how it functioned and
that's much more expensive, but that can be done by the very
rich ones. So מאי שמן המור *mai shemen hamor*, what is this
שמן המור *shemen hamor*? Myrrh oil is normally how it would be
interpreted. Myrrh is like a fragrance, right? So presumably it would just
be oil steeped in the fragrance. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says,
what is that? רב יהודה בר ירמיה אמר סתכת, Rav Yehudah bar
Yirmyah amar satachet, which רש"י Rashi says לא אתפרש, lo itparesh, doesn't
know what that is. So but something called סתכת. satachet. All right,
anything there?
This says olive oil. Olive oil?
Yeah. Okay, there's other words for olive oil than סתכת. satachet. Anyway,
okay. סתכת. satachet.
It even says שמן זית. shemen zayit.
I think I think you're going ahead. That's the next statement. רב
ירמיה בר אבא אמר שמן זית שלא הביא שליש,
Rav Yirmyah bar Abba
amar
shemen zayit shelo hevia shalish, olive oil from olives that have not
ripened a third, from unripe olives. Yeah. Okay, so maybe that had
the ability to make the hair fall off. תניא רבי יהודה אומר
אנפיקינון, Tania Rabbi Yehudah omer anpikanon, that word אנפיקינון, anpikanon, which is
a which is something that's identified in another Rabbinic discussion if you
want to know what that is, that comes up in a discussion
in מנחות, Menachot, that's שמן זית שלא הביא שליש. shemen zayit shelo
hevia shalish. It's the same thing. It's olive oil made from olives
that are unripe. ולמה סכין אותו? Ulamma sachin oto? And why did
they use this to rub on their skin? מפני שמשיר את השיער,
Mipnei shemashir et hase'ar, it causes the hair to fall off, which
is clearly what the concern was, and number two, if you're using
oil, ומעדן את הבשר, umeadenn et habasar, it softens the skin. Okay.
So anyway you see though that there are some types of of
women's cosmetics that are flower-based and therefore רב אליעזר Rav Eliezer includes
those. Not exactly clear what he's arguing with the חכמים chachamim about
because if they're flower-based, then shouldn't the חכמים chachamim agree?
So anyway, what's the problem with them? We haven't really discussed the
חמץ. chametz, No, but I mean you're not going to eat
you know so we'll talk about that. I mean it's not necessarily
presumably it's at least ראוי לאכילת כלב, ra'ui l'achilat kelev, okay? So
it's not completely inedible. But we will so let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara is not done. We're going to get to discussing
categories in a minute. זה הכלל כל שהוא ממין דגן. Ze haklal
kol shehu mimmim dagan. This is the principle. Anything that's made of
some type of a grain is a problem, has a grain content.
תנו רבנן אמר רבי יהושע. Tanu Rabbanan amar Rabbi Yehoshua. So we
said רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, כי מאחר
ששנינו. kime'achar sheshaninu. Very interesting, because here you have a תנא Tanna
reflecting on a משנה Mishnah, saying since, and again notice, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua is a תנא, Tanna, say, well, if the משנה Mishnah.
was anyway going to say, normally you assume like you know the
תנאים Tannaim precede the משנה, mishna? the actual editing of the משנה,
mishna, but maybe this was a line, as I've said to you
in the past, that you know רבי Rebbi did a job of
an editor not of an author, and this might have been a
teaching
of, you know, these things might have been a teaching that were
preceded some of the תנאים. Tannaim. So he so says רבי יהושע
דכי מאחר ששנינו כל שהוא ממין דגן הרי זה עובר בפסח, Rabbi
Yehoshua deki me'achar sheshaninu kol shehu mimmim dagan harei ze over bePesach,
if we already have a teaching that everything that is a type
of a grain that has grain content is forbidden on פסח, Pesach,
למה מנו חכמים את אלו? lamma manu chachamim et elu? So why
did we bother making a list? Right? Just tell me the general
rule. So that's you know so that's often like we get frustrated
because sometimes a lot of things like here you have a lot
of specifics but we want to know like what's the rule, what's
the underlying principle? So he says well if you have an underlying
principle anything that has a grain content, who needs the specifics? Now
obviously both of them serve an important function because if you have
a principle it's too abstract and to get a sense of some
of its application and some of its contours and some of its
parameters, you know, concrete examples are very helpful. Examples by themselves are
not so great because then you don't know how to apply it
elsewhere. But that's his question. His question is once we have the
rule, who needs the examples? למה מנו חכמים את אלו? Lamma manu
chachamim et elu? And the answer is כדי שיהא רגיל בהן ובשמותיהן,
kedei sheyehe ragil bahen ubeshemotehen, in order that you should be familiarized
with yourself with them and with their names. Now that is the
end of רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua statement. So the obvious follow-up question
is, who cares to know them and their names as long as
we know the principle? So the גמרא Gemara now has an addition
and you see the shift here from Hebrew to Aramaic. כי הא
דהוא בר מערבא, Ki ha dehu bar maarava, like the case of
a person from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, איקלע לבבל, iklei l'bavel, came
to בבל. Bavel. הוה בישרא בהדיה, Havi bisra bahadei, and this forget
it it wasn't פסח, Pesach, סתם, stam, he had some meat. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, and he said to the people whoever he was
staying at or the inn, קריבו לי מתחלתא, kribu li matchilta, could
you please bring me some dip for my meat? שמע דקאמרי, Shama
d'kanre, and then he heard them talking and saying, קריבו ליה כותח,
kribu le kuthach, go bring him some כותח. kutach, So they didn't
know that he had meat, maybe he just said I need some
dip. כיון דשמע כותח, Keivan d'shama kuthach, he heard the name כותח,
kutach אה פירש. oh pirash. Then he said, "Oh forget it, I'll
pass," because he had learned that כותח kutach was a type of
a dip that had milk that was made with sour milk. So
you see because you're familiar with what types of you know foods
there are out there and what they're called, that'll be a helpful
helpful information in general when you're navigating the world of כשרות kashrut
and of פסח Pesach and so on to be familiar with foods
and what's in them. Like I sometimes tell my students when we're
learning כשרות, kashrut, you know there's a whole thing about you know
look at the ingredients. So there's a question, can you look at
the ingredients or not? Some actually you know some some people in
the כשרות kashrut world say if you really know what you're looking
at then you can totally rely on looking at the ingredients. You
know others don't agree. I'm not going to have that discussion right
now, but I tell them if you're looking at the ingredients, you
know the ingredient you have to be most careful about. is the
one that says
natural flavors because natural flavors sounds totally innocent. Oh, probably they made
it, what, from fruits, from whatever? Natural flavors they make from, like
if you're getting, they make from sometimes like ground up ants. They'll
make from I mean they really make some of these natural colors
and flavors from real like טרפה traif things, you know? Like food
coloring is made from ground up ants and other types of things.
Anyway, so if you're רגיל בהן ובשמותיהן, ragil bahen u-vi-shmoteihen, you know
what types of things to look out for. So okay, that's not
really a פסח Pesach point per se, but תוספות Tosafot does he
doesn't even understand the question because תוספות Tosafot says look, you know,
obviously we have to list that because we have to know, you
know, first of all that there's it's not enough to say it
has grain in it. We just got through saying anyway that there's
two conceptual categories. There's a category of תערובת, taaruvet, of a mixture,
there's a category of חמץ נוקשה, chametz nuksha of something that isn't
a mixture but isn't really so edible, you know? So obviously we
need some examples to have some sense of the parameters. תוספות Tosafot
says yeah, but why didn't we need all of these examples? That's
the question. Why do we need all of these examples? And the
answer is it's helpful to have specifics as well. Okay. So now
we get finally to turn to the question of what are these
categories and how do we know they're forbidden? הרי אלו באזהרה. Harei
elu ba-azharah. These things there's a negative prohibition if you eat them
but you do not get כרת, kares so there's some middle level
of חמץ. chametz
So
the גמרא Gemara, says מאן תנא דחמץ דגן גמור על ידי תערובת
ונוקשה בעיניה בלאו. Man tanna de-chametz dagan gamur al yedei taaruvet ve-nuksha
be-einei be-lav. So here the גמרא Gemara in six words gives you
the conceptual categorization of these two things on the list. חמץ דגן
גמור, chametz dagan gamur, pure חמץ, chametz real fermented bread, or maybe
the barley with the water really ferments, but it's על ידי תערובת.
al yedei taaruvet. It's in a mixture with other things. So that
would be the כותח kutach, dip that had the moldy bread but
it would also be like the, you know, the barley that's put
into the wine to ferment because you've got the wine and you've
got the fermented barley. Okay. So those are real על ידי תערובת.
al yedei taaruvet. But again, I want to make it clear the
reason I mentioned the barley is because we're not only speaking about
bread, right? We're speaking about, you know, even things that isn't bread
but that fully ferments, it's a food, but it's על ידי תערובת.
al yedei taaruvet. That's category one. Category two is נוקשה בעיניה. nuksha
be-einei. By itself, not in a תערובת, taaruvet, on its own, but
it's נוקשה. nuksha. Now נוקשה nuksha is a technical word and נוקשה
nuksha basically means as I said one of two
things. נוקשה, nuksha, for example, we're about to see a case that
the גמרא Gemara speaks about, you have your dough and it started
to ferment but it hasn't fully fermented. Like there's a discussion what
that stage is where you start seeing like it starts expanding, where
you start seeing some cracks in the in the dough but it
hasn't fully fermented. That's called נוקשה. nuksha. There, the reason it's in
a lesser category seems to be maybe that it is not hasn't
had full fermentation. But the other thing that also gets included in
this נוקשה nuksha category is stuff that's not really that edible like
all these types of various plasters and so on, glues and plasters,
etc. So נוקשה nuksha seems to include both of those, not fully
edible, not fully fermented. Maybe there's an assumption that both are true,
it's not exactly clear or either are true. Yes, Charlie.
I've got a question. Where would pasta fall? It's flour and water
but it doesn't ferment, it's just
dry.
How do you do? You lay it flat and you leave it
out and then you bake it or you leave it out to
dry?
You leave it out and dry it.
So how does it not ferment?
Because there's nothing there's no yeast, there's no leaven and it dries
quite quickly.
But doesn't but if you just have if you just make dough
with flour and water, right? Are you telling me that that there
will be no fermentation that will occur or just won't rise like
bread?
It won't rise like bread.
But right. So I assume it would be no different than like
the pita, right? Because you could make, you know, if you make
pita...
I put yeast when I make pita. Aha.
Well for the גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara does not require the
addition of, you know, of a leavening agent for for...
so pasta would be
yeah, pasta is considered חמץ דגן גמור chametz dagan gamur even if
it doesn't rise. But you are right when it does describe how
you identify fermentation, it talks about rising bread and seeing it sort
of expand and seeing the cracks and so on. So yeah.
To conceptualize this, is חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha as the second way
you explained it, sort of the חמץ chametz equivalent to מאכל בן
דרוסאי? ma'achal ben drosai?
No, it would be... it would be more like, you know, ראוי
לאכילת כלב rau'i le-akhilat kelev and not ראוי לאכילת אדם. rau'i le-akhilat
adam.
And where do we see that ראוי לאכילת כלב rau'i le-akhilat kelev
is such a big deal?
We don't well we haven't yet, okay, although... so but look, that's
the discussion that we're in the middle of. Okay, so let's keep
on going a little bit a little bit further. So it says
like this,
yeah I'll read you what רש״י Rashi says about the word נוקשה.
nuksha. רש״י Rashi says... רש״י Rashi
about 10 lines 12 no 15 lines down in the narrow lines,
רש״י Rashi says like this, נוקשה, nuksha, the word is נוקשה nuksha
at the beginning of the line about 15 lines down in the
narrow
lines, רש״י Rashi says... איכא נמי חמץ נוקשה. Ika nami chametz nuksha.
It's bad חמץ, chametz, it's not so edible, but it's in its
own, it's not mixed up with other
things. מוזהרין על אכילתו בלאו דתניא ב muzarim al achilaso belav detanya
be חמשת דברים הללו ושיכר המדי, chamesh devarim halalu veshechar hamadai, חמץ
דגן גמור chametz dagan gamur אלא שנתערב בדבר אחר, ela shenisarav bedavar
acher, ותכשיטי נשים, vesachshitei nashim, women's types of cosmetics, בעיניהו, be'ineihu, that's
the original way, it's not mixed with anything, these like the the
dough depilatory, אבל נוקשה הוא aval nuksha hu דאינו ראוי לאכילה. de'eino
ra'uy lachila. Okay, so here רש"י Rashi defines נוקשה nuksha as אינו
ראוי לאכילה, eino ra'uy lachila, but in an case we're about to
see, it also includes cases of stuff that hasn't fermented completely. All
right, so exactly, I mean if it's completely אינו ראוי לאכילה eino
ra'uy lachila it's not an issue, and that becomes this middle category
of ראוי לאכילה כלב, ra'uy lachila kelev, but we have yet to
identify it as such.
Like the Play-Doh thing?
Right, exactly. So now the גמרא Gemara, continues. Okay. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב רבי מאיר היא. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Rabi Meir
hi. So who is this תנא tanna that has this middle category?
So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda, in the name of רב says it's
רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, דתניא detanya we taught in the ברייתא, braisa,
שאור ישרף. se'or yisaref. Now שאור se'or is not the same as
שאור. se'or. שאור se'or
is sourdough that can be used as a leavening agent. שאור se'or
is the stage I was describing to you, which is the bread
before it has fully fermented. You've got your dough
and it is starting to expand, there are some cracks in it,
but it's not enough to be considered fully fermented. It's this middle
category that's called שאור. se'or. There's a debate what stage that is,
the debate of רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda and רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir,
but it's before it's defined to be fully fermented. So what do
you do with it? So the הברייתא ha'braisa says ישרף, yisaref, you
have to burn it, even though it's not yet fully fermented, ויתנו
לכלבו, veyisno lechalbo, or give it to your dog. So the גמרא
Gemara, is going to say that's a contradiction. Burning is what you
do when you're not allowed to derive benefit, giving it to your
dog means you can still derive benefit. We'll get back to that.
והאוכלו בארבעים, veha'ochlo be'arba'im, and if you eat it, you do not
get כרת, kares, but you get forty lashes. So that's what we're
going to focus on, that idea that there's a stage a type
of a חמץ chametz that you do not get the כרת kares,
for but you get lashes for that falls in this middle category.
So first the גמרא gemara has to unpack this ברייתא. braisa. It
says הגופא קשיא, hagufa kashya, this is internally contradictory. הגופא קשיא, hagufa
kashya, where is
it?
אמרת שאור ישרף, amarta se'or yisaref, first you say burn it, אלמא
אסור בהנאה, alma asur behana'a, you can't derive
benefit. והדר תני ונתנו לפני כלבו, vehadar tani unseno lifnei chalbo, give
it to your dog, אלמא מותר בהנאה, alma mutar behana'a, you see
you're allowed to derive benefit. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what
it
means. שאור ישרף, se'or yisaref, אליבא דרבי מאיר אליבא דרבי יהודה. aliba
deRabi Meir aliba deRabi Yehuda. There's a debate of רבי מאיר Rabi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda at what stage is it considered
שאור. se'or. רבי מאיר Rabi Meir says an earlier stage than רבי
יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. Let's say the following. Let's say what it says
at stage one, everybody agrees, we'll get to the details later, so
that's why we're not worrying about it now, everybody agrees it hasn't
yet begun fermenting. Stage four, everybody agrees that it's full חמץ. chametz
Okay, how about stages two and three? So רבי מאיר Rabi Meir
says it's already problematic at two, שאור, se'or, and רבי יהודה Rabi
Yehuda says it's only problematic at three. So רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir,
when it's
רבי מאיר's Rabi Meir's stage, problematic stage two, then it's ישרף yisaref
you gotta burn it, רבי יהודה, Rabi Yehuda, for רבי יהודה, Rabi
Yehuda, when it gets to his problematic stage three you have to
burn it. So that's when you have to burn it and it's
אסור בהנאה, asur behana'a, when it is actually hits that level of
real
שאור. se'or. ונתנו לפני כלבו, unseno lifnei chalbo, how about the line
of giving it to your dog, which means it's מותר בהנאה, mutar
behana'a, what that means is אליבא דרבי מאיר לרבי יהודה, aliba deRabi
Meir leRabi Yehuda, when it's at רבי מאיר's Rabi Meir's stage of
being a problem, number two, but from רבי יהודה's Rabi Yehuda's opinion,
right, you got it? So רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says only when
it hits three does it hit this שאור se'or level. What do
I say about stage number two, which רבי מאיר Rabi Meir thinks
is a problem? I don't think that's a real problem, so I'll
say you can still get הנאה hana'a from it, give it to
your dog, okay, you can't eat it, but I'll halfway meet רבי
מאיר Rabi Meir at that stage. Why not ישרף yisaref now though?
No, it's ישרף yisaref when it hits what the level you say
is a problem. So if you're רבי מאיר Rabi Meir it's ישרף
yisaref at two, if you're רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda it's ישרף yisaref
at three. But the ונתנו לפני כלבו unseno lifnei chalbo is what
רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda would say when it was at stage two.
Like it's pizza hour, like totally?
Yeah, exactly, like that debate. Okay, anyway, we don't have to get
caught up in that. ארכי archi is the next line, והאוכלו בארבעים,
veha'ochlo be'arba'im, but if you eat it you get forty, אתאן לרבי
מאיר, asan leRabi Meir, that's if you're talking about stage two, that's
according to רבי מאיר. Rabi Meir. It could have also said it's
רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda for stage three, but however the way it
structures this, since the end we're talking about the earlier stage, it
says that therefore that's a רבי מאיר Rabi Meir position. Anyway, what
you see from this is that this שאור, se'or, this middle level,
you get lashes but you don't get כרת, kares. so you see
that there's this middle category. שמעינן ליה לרבי מאיר, shaminan lei leRabi
Meir, therefore we can infer from this, we hear from רבי מאיר,
Rabi Meir, דנוקשה בעיניה בלאו, denuksha be'ineia belav, that נוקשה nuksha is
when even by itself, all you have here is dough, it's a
negative prohibition but not כרת, kares, it's this middle category. Now again,
why is this נוקשה? nuksha? Is it נוקשה nuksha because if you
were to make it at this stage it wouldn't be so, it
wouldn't be edible? Really? So like I can go ahead and make
stuff that hasn't fermented at all and have it מצה matzah and
it's edible. I can have stuff that's totally fermented and make bread
and that's edible. But if it's quasi-fermented it's not edible? So here's
why you see that the idea of נוקשה nuksha seems to include
not just the non-edible category but the non-fully fermented category. Okay so
there are two things that seem to be in this נוקשה: nuksha:
not fully fermented or not really edible. Okay and either way it's
not completely חמץ, chametz but it's enough to be a middle category
of you get a לאו, lav, a negative prohibition.
But that didn't answer your question.
So that's the point, my point is that it's not that it's
not edible, that you see from this that נוקשה nuksha includes not
only the not edible category but נוקשה nuksha includes the not fully
fermented category. But it still doesn't include not edible? Yes, it includes
both.
It's not one or the other, I mean it's not one and
the
other, it's one or the other. Correct, correct. Yes. Yes, so נוקשה
nuksha includes both both there are two types of different things it
could be called נוקשה: nuksha: not edible or not fully
fermented. Okay, so שמיענו ליה לרבי מאיר נוקשה בעיני בלאו. shaminu lei
l'Rebbe Meir nuksha be-enei belav. So you see now that רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir says that this middle category, not fully fermented and also
he said not edible or fully edible is the negative prohibition. And
if he says
that, חמץ דגן גמור ידי תערובת, chametz dagan gamur yedei ta'aroves, if
you say that's a negative prohibition, certainly if you have real חמץ
chametz, it's just mixed up with other things, certainly that would be
a negative prohibition. Okay, now
so he assumes that like this is going to be the question
of what's the hierarchy, which is the thing that's more obviously forbidden.
For this statement of the גמרא, Gemara רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda who
was it who said this, רב יהודה in the name of רב,
it's much more obvious that real חמץ chometz in a תערובת ta'aroves
is more forbidden than this. So if this is forbidden, certainly real
חמץ chometz in a תערובת. ta'aroves. That's one way of identifying the
author of the משנה. mishna, רב נחמן אמר רבי אליעזר היא, Rav
Nachman amar Rebbe Eliezer hi, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer it is. דתניא, d'tanya, ברייתא, braisa, חמץ דגן גמור עונשו
כרת, chametz dagan gamur onosho kares, if you have full חמץ, chometz
full bread, full full חמץ chometz you get כרת. kares, על עירובו
בלאו, al eruvo belav, if it's in a תערובת, ta'aroves, בלאו belav
you get a negative prohibition. So that's a very clear statement that
חמץ chometz, in a תערובת ta'aroves is not כרת, kares. it's a
middle category of a negative prohibition. דברי רבי אליעזר, divrei Rebbe Eliezer,
that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and
the חכמים Chachamim say, חמץ דגן גמור עונשו כרת chametz dagan gamur
onosho kares on full חמץ chometz you get כרת, kares. על עירובו
al eruvo if it's in a תערובת, ta'aroves, בלאו כלום, belav klum,
you don't transgress anything. I guess that's, I bet that's coming as
a pretty big surprise for people, right? Yeah. And let me take
a moment here to reflect on this. Because if I would have
said to you, let's say you've got your
moldy little pieces of bread and you mixed it up into a
into some type of I don't know a sour cream or something
to the point that it's dissolved, you can't exactly see it. It's
not like it's there just with other stuff alongside of it. And
you ate it. What do you think the prohibition would be? Probably
most of us would say כרת. kares Yeah, I mean you ate
real חמץ, chometz okay, it's not בטל, batel, we know there's an
idea of ביטול, bittul, but if like in the mixtures we saw
before, a third this, a third that, a third that, it's not
בטל, batel, it's not בטל, batel, you get כרת. kares So what
is this discussion, is it a לאו, lav, is it nothing? I
mean how could it be nothing? So I will say that whether
you get כרת kares. there's in general a debate of ראשונים Rishonim
that when you have something forbidden in a תערובת ta'aroves and it's
not בטל batel because of the principle of טעם כעיקר, ta'am k'ikar,
the taste prevents ביטול, bittul, there's a question of whether you
still considered the same prohibition. So if I get like I don't
know blood which is כרת kares. and I mix it up with
a in in my soup and it's not בטל, batel, some will
say okay it's still prohibited but it's a different prohibition. It's not
the prohibition of blood, it's a different prohibition of the taste of
blood or it's a derivative of the prohibition of blood or something
like that and therefore maybe it's a negative prohibition but maybe you
don't get כרת. kares, That's what some say, but everybody at least
agrees, others say no it's exactly the prohibition of blood and you
get כרת. kares. But everybody agrees that it's biblically prohibited, that's the
principle of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. So what is the issue here?
So I will say and we'll get back to this tomorrow on
שבת, Shabbos, there's an important debate of the ראשונים rishonim about what
type of what are we talking about when we talk about this
תערובת ta'aroves and whether it gets לאו lav or nothing etc. Are
we talking about that it's a type of a mixture that has
the proportions, this will be a major discussion tomorrow in the גמרא,
gemara but I want to introduce it here, the proportions of כזית
בכדי אכילת פרס k'zayis bichdei achilas pras or less than those proportions.
כזית k'zayis is a normal amount you have to eat to transgress,
אכילת פרס achilas pras is normally the amount of time that if
you eat a כזית k'zayis of whatever חזיר chazir over the time
it takes to eat half a loaf of bread, which is normally
I don't know five minutes nine minutes, then it all combined and
it's like you ate a full כזית k'zayis at once and you
get lashes. If you eat it over a longer period of time
then you never ate a full כזית k'zayis at once and you
don't get lashes. That's normally the amount of time it takes. It's
also a ratio, a פרס pras is about eight to nine כזיתים
k'zeisim so it's a one to eight one to nine ratio. If
you have a תערובת ta'aroves that has less than this proportion, right,
so it's less than a כזית k'zayis in the time takes to
eat a פרס pras and I eat this כותח, kutach but if
I eat this כותח even if I'm eating it straight over nine
minutes I will never have ingested a כזית k'zayis of bread during
that time so... Then you say, oh, well, then I understand that
it's not the normal prohibition, cause you'll never be able to eat
a כזית kezayis in the requisite amount of time. That's why I
might need a new prohibition called חמץ בתערובת, chometz betaarovas because even
if I say there's an issue of טעם כעיקר, taam ke'ikar, it's
not enough to get lashes because you'll never eat enough because of
its proportion in the ratio. So a number of ראשונים rishonim think
that the reason you need a new prohibition of חמץ chometz in
a mixture is we're talking about types of mixtures which you'll never
eat enough a כזית kezayis of חמץ chometz, in the right amount
of time to actually transgress the standard prohibition. So therefore we create
a new prohibition called it exists as a percentage in a mixture
and it's אסור assur as תערובת חמץ, tarovet chametz. not necessarily because
you ate חמץ chometz, in X amount of time, it's אסור assur
because this whole thing is called תערובת חמץ. tarovet chametz That is
the way a lot of ראשונים rishonim. understand, but I do want
to point out that there's another possibility as well, an even more
radical possibility. And this is a possibility that
has to do with the fact that חמץ chometz, is not the
same as חזיר. chazir. That even though or דם, dam, even though
by דם dam if it's in a mixture, let's say, and I
eat it and it's כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, kezayis bichedei achilas pras,
let's say we get כרת, kareit? I might not say the same
by חמץ, chometz even if it is כזית בכדי אכילת פרס kezayis
bichedei achilas pras in a mixture. Why not? Because חמץ chometz is,
as remember before when we also dealt with issues about like מצה
matzah and לחם, lechem, and we compared it to issues about taking,
you know, taking חלה challah and the definition of לחם lechem is
חמץ chametz actually the same as like, you know, the fact that
you have something that is fermented, or is part of the definition
of חמץ chametz also like לחם חמץ? lechem chometz? You know, חמץ,
chametz לחם, lechem, or whatever, you know, they're almost the same words,
חמץ, chametz, לחם, lechem, and מצה. matzah. Do you see all the
overlaps of letters between those words there, right? לחם, lechem, חמץ, chametz.
מצה, matzah, right? So anyway, if it's, if part of its identity
is bread, not fermented grain, right, but it's bread, then when it's
בתערובת, betaarovas, can I say that I have bread בתערובת? betaarovas? Or
once it's בתערובת, betaarovas, I no longer have bread here, right? So
its identity as bread has to do with the form that it
takes, not just the material that it's made out of. That's different
than anything else. If I have blood בתערובת betaarovas or חזיר בתערובת,
chazir betaarovas, I have some pork in my stew, I have some
blood in my stew. But bread, maybe it stops being bread and
it just comes, becomes more the, you know, sort of the
ingredients that it's made out of. It has fermented, you know, fermented
grain is there but no longer bread. So beer, by definition, beer
by
definition according to that would be a תערובת. taarovas.
Right, because you have, right, so it never becomes bread, and that's
why the גמרא Gemara before spoke about
barley and making beer and so on. At the time I said
it has other things other than just the water, it's got wine,
it's got the mead, but maybe even if it was just the
water and the barley, maybe it would always be considered תערובת taarovas
because it never actually becomes לחם. lechem. Even if it's כזית בכדי
אכילת פרס. kezayis bichedei achilas pras. So that is the opinion of
some ראשונים. rishonim Some ראשונים rishonim actually say that even כזית בכדי
אכילת פרס, kezayis bichedei achilas pras, okay, for when it comes to
חמץ chametz. would need a separate category of חמץ בתערובת chametz betarovet,
and it would not be the same as others. Yes.
It's also reasonable to say if in the mixtures that you're talking
about, דם dam and so on, what's the word where it's still,
you can still identify the piece of איסור? issur?
נותן טעם? nosein taam? Oh no, it's ניכר. nikar.
Yeah, right, but blood is a liquid. As soon as you put
it in another liquid, it's all mixed together and it's...
Right, but don't, but you have blood in here, right? You have
blood in your soup. A certain percentage of your soup has blood,
right? So would you say that a certain percentage of my
soup has bread if the bread has completely dissolved? You might say
I put bread in my soup to make it, but if I
said like what are the ingredients, to me it's different because again,
maybe I'm not articulating well, but to me it seems like that
it loses its identity. It's not just that it's there but you,
it's mixed in, it stops being bread. It's more the materials it
was made out of, but bread has to do with the form,
not just with its substance. Anyway, that's I think how a number
of ראשונים understand this, and that is the debate: whether we say
בתערובת betaarovas is not just אסור assur because like anything else is
אסור בתערובת. assur betaarovas. So some say it's because there's not enough
of it to be a problem, it's less than כזית בכדי אכילת
פרס, kezayis bichedei achilas pras, and some say it's the unique idea
that חמץ chametz, is actually part of its identity is bread, and
that identity is lost when it's בתערובת. betaarovas. Charlie.
Why wouldn't this fall under חצי שיעור אסור מן התורה? chatzi shiur
assur min hatorah?
It would. You mean the כזית בכדי אכילת פרס kezayis bichedei achilas
pras issue? Yeah, but it's still not, but you would never get
מלקות malkus for that. So we still would need, you're right, nobody
would say it's מותר mutar to eat less than כזית בכדי אכילת
פרס, kezayis bichedei achilas pras, but the need for a separate לאו
lav and מלקות malkus is to make it more severe. Yes.
I see all these distinctions, but is this ultimately based on a
פסוק? pasuk?
We're getting there! We haven't read, okay, let's take a look. Okay,
so it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that it's בתערובת, betaarovas,
it gets a לאו lav and not כרת. kareit And the חכמים
chachamim say you don't even get a לאו. lav.
Even if there's
no...
That's my point, that's my bigger point. Why do you need a
separate לאו lav if there is טעם? taam? And that's the two
reasons I gave you, either because of a unique nature of bread
or because that it's the percentage, the quantity of it is so
little and therefore this makes it more forbidden because you know because
of this new identity as תערובת חמץ. ta'arovet chametz. Okay,
וחכמים אומרים חמץ דגן גמור ענוש כרת על עירובו בלא כלום. V'hachamim
omrim chametz dagan gamur anush kareit al eiruvo belo klum. ושמעינן ליה
לרבי אליעזר דאמר, U'shameinan lei l'Rabbi Eliezer d'amar, so now we know
that Rabbi Eliezer says חמץ דגן גמור על ידי תערובת בלאו, chametz
dagan gamur al yedei tarovet b'lav, that in a mixture it's a
negative prohibition. So if that's forbidden, כל שכן? kal vachomer? No, נוקשה
בעיני, nuksha b'einay, how much more so if it was חמץ נוקשה
chametz nuksha? which was all by itself, which wasn't in a mixture.
So this is a debate of which is more obviously forbidden. According
to the first approach it was more obviously forbidden if it was
real חמץ chametz. in a mixture. So if נוקשה nuksha is forbidden
certainly a mixture, and in this it's the opposite. It's more obvious
if it's נוקשה nuksha by itself, so if so if a mixture
is forbidden, certainly certainly נוקשה nuksha by itself. But basically they basically
say one has a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying נוקשה, nuksha, one
has a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying תערובת, tarovet, and we're assuming
that one of those is the תנא tanna that actually holds both
of those is forbidden. Okay,
ורב נחמן מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב יהודה? V'Rav Nachman mai ta'ama
lo amar k'Rav Yehuda? Why did Rav Nachman not like Rav Yehuda's
answer that it was Rabbi Meir who spoke about חמץ chametz נוקשה?
nuksha אמר לך, Amar lach, because he it's obvious, he has his
hierarchy different. דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם, Dilma ad
kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Meir hatam, when did Rabbi Meir say there's
a it's forbidden? אלא נוקשה בעיני, Ella nuksha b'einay,
that's נוקשה nuksha when it's not mixed in other things. אבל חמץ
דגן גמור על ידי תערובת, Aval chametz dagan gamur al yedei tarovet,
but real חמץ chametz that's mixed in other things, לא, lo, that
is not as obviously forbidden. So I can't infer from Rabbi Meir
to apply it to the case of a mixture. ורב יהודה מאי
טעמא לא אמר כרב נחמן? V'Rav Yehuda mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rav
Nachman? So why didn't Rav Yehuda like Rav Nachman's evidence of Rabbi
Eliezer and that he's the author of the משנה? Mishnah Same argument,
I mean same point in reverse. אמר לך עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי אליעזר התם, Amar lach ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer hatam,
yes I concede that Rabbi Eliezer said it's forbidden, אלא חמץ דגן
גמור על ידי תערובת, ella chametz dagan gamur al yedei tarovet, real
חמץ chametz, in a mixture. אבל נוקשה בעיני, Aval nuksha b'einay, but
if it's something like but if it's נוקשה nuksha, which is which
is it's true it's by itself but nevertheless it's not real חמץ,
chametz, it's only נוקשה, nuksha, לא אמר, lo amar, maybe he wouldn't
say it. So basically we have one תנא tanna Rabbi Meir that
says נוקשה, nuksha one תנא tanna Rabbi Eliezer that says תערובת, tarovet,
and what we assume that one of them would actually agree to
you know would say the other thing as well. It's just not
clear which is the one which is considered more lenient and which
is considered more severe. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
תניא כוותיה דרב יהודה. Tanya k'vatei d'Rav Yehuda. We turned like Rav
Yehuda that said that this makes it go like
Rabbi Eliezer—I'm sorry, that goes like Rabbi Meir. Where does it say?
כל מחמצת לא תאכלו, Kol machmetzet lo tocheilu, so you shall not
eat any מחמצת, machmetzet, כל, kol, so it has the word any,
and מחמצת, machmetzet, not חמץ. chametz. So מחמצת machmetzet is being read
to be understood like any any even residual חמץ. chametz, No. No.
Yeah, that's not how it's being read here, we'll see. לרבות כותח
הבבלי ושכר המדי וחומץ האדומי וזיתום המצרי, L'rabot kutach habavli v'shachar hamadi
v'chometz ha'adomi v'zeitum hamitzri,
to include all of these types of things which was basically חמץ
chametz, בתערובת, be-ta'arovet. okay? So that's כל מחמצת. kol machmetzet. So that's
somehow from כל מחמצת, kol machmetzet, from the כל kol either from
the כל kol or from the מחמצת. machmetzet. יכול יהא ענוש כרת?
Yachol yehei anush kareit?
Maybe if it's forbidden you get כרת? kareit. So the גמרא Gemara
says, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the verse teaches, כי כל אוכל
חמץ ונכרתה, Ki kol ochel chametz v'nichreta,
anybody that eats חמץ, chametz, not מחמצת. machmetzet. For כרת kares. you
need real חמץ. chametz, על חמץ דגן גמור ענוש כרת, Al chametz
dagan gamur anush kareit, for real חמץ chametz, you get כרת. kares
על עירובו, Al eiruvo, which is the word מחמצת, machmetzet, which is
like residual you know sort of like you know in the in
the you know in the ambit of חמץ chametz, but not full
חמץ, chametz. על עירובו al eiruvo so it's a mixture of חמץ,
chametz, בלאו, belav, that's a negative prohibition. Okay, so that's learning from
the פסוק pasuk this idea of חמץ דגן גמור. chametz dagan gamur.
מאן שמעת ליה דאמר על עירובו בלאו? Man shamat lei d'amar al
eiruvo belav? Who is this one that says תערובת חמץ ta'arovet chametz,
you get a negative prohibition? רבי אליעזר היא. Rabbi Eliezer hi. He
says Rabbi Eliezer. ואילו נוקשה בעיני, V'ilu nuksha b'einay, but regarding נוקשה
nuksha, by itself, the last cases of the משנה, Mishna the more
sort of medicinal or glues or whatever, לא קאמר, lo ka'amar, so
you he didn't say. So you're learning it from the פסוק pasuk
and he learns out all these mixtures, and he if he held
that included in the category of forbidden things was נוקשה, nuksha, he
should have said it. So you see that since here he's giving
specifics and he lists all the stuff in the beginning of the
משנה, Mishna, he's not just speaking in generalities. So he's being specific
and he didn't mention any examples of נוקשה, nuksha. שמע מינה נוקשה
לרבי אליעזר לית ליה. Shema mina nuksha l'Rabbi Eliezer leit lei. You
see that Rabbi Eliezer doesn't hold of נוקשה. nuksha, You see that
Rabbi Eliezer right until now everything's been talking in very much generalities.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir talks about שאור. se'or. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
talks about חמץ על ידי תערובת. chametz al yedei tarovet. But finally
we have a ברייתא braita where Rabbi Eliezer gives you the פסוק
pasuk and very clearly identifies all the things that are included, and
even so he doesn't mention נוקשה, nukshah, so you see that Rabbi
Eliezer is only a תערובת. tarovet. man, he's not a נוקשה Nuksha.
*nuksha* man. So if you want to find somebody that holds of
both, the bet is on רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbe Meir*. רבי
מאיר *Rebbe Meir* holds of נוקשה *nuksha* so maybe he also holds
of תערובת ta'aroves, *ta'aroves*. But we're going to assume that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbe Eliezer* only holds of תערובת ta'aroves, *ta'aroves* and does
not hold of נוקשה *nuksha*. Okay, that's in terms of the authorship
of the משנה *mishnah*. But now we get to the more focused
discussion of this category of חמץ chametz, בתערובת be-ta'arovet, *chametz b'ta'aroves* and
that it falls into this middle category of a negative prohibition and
not כרת kares. *kares*. So let's take a look. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rebbe Eliezer* עירוב בלאו מנא ליה *eruv b'lav m'na lei*? So
now let's go back to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rebbe Eliezer*. Where
does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbe Eliezer* know that the mixture of
חמץ chametz. *chametz* is a negative prohibition? דכתיב *dichsiv* it says כל
מחמצת kol machmetzes לא תאכלו *kol machmetzes lo socheilu*. Don't eat any
מחמצת machmetzes *machmetzes* which is learned to be even less than חמץ
chametz. *chametz*. Anything that contains חמץ chametz? *chametz*. אי הכי *i hachi*
כרת kares נמי ליחייב *kares nami l'mechayeiv*. If that's what מחמצת *machmetzes*
means, so you should also get כרת kares *kares*. דהא כתיב *deha
ksiv* the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says כי כל אוכל ki kol ochel,
מחמצת ונכרתה *ki kol ochel machmetzes venichresa*. There's another פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*
that says if you eat מחמצת *machmetzes* you get כרת kares? *kares*.
So if מחמצת *machmetzes* is mixture, so you should also get כרת
karet, *kares*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא *hahu
mibayei lei l'chid'tanya*. No, no, no. That's teaching you something else like
what Michael said. אין לי אלא שנתחמץ מאליו *ein li ela shenischametz
me'elav*. I only know something is called חמץ chametz *chametz* if it
ferments by itself meaning without something added like, you know, other than
sourdough. Sourdough is considered by itself because it's still flour and water
based. But without some external type of a leavening agent like yeast.
נתחמץ מחמת דבר אחר מנין *nischametz machamas davar acher minayin*? How do
I know if it became חמץ chametz *chametz* because of something else
like, you know, yeast or baking powder or whatever? How do I
know that even that's called חמץ chametz, *chametz*? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar,
מחמצת ונכרתה *talmud lomar machmetzes venichresa*. So here the word מחמצת *machmetzes*
as opposed to חמץ chametz *chametz* is learned to understand like, you
know, I think it's the הפעיל *hif'il* form. Something else effected the
חמץ chametz *chametz*. So something else was a leavening agent and even
so you're not חייב *chayav* for the leavening agent but you're חייב
*chayav* for the bread that resulted. So מחמצת *machmetzes* here teaches you,
so מחמצת *machmetzes* means something that's not paradigmatic חמץ chametz, *chametz*. So
in the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* that says that you get כרת karet.
*kares* we say it means because you had added some leavening agent
and that's when you get כרת karet. *kares*. In the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* that says you have a negative prohibition but where we're going
to say no כרת karet *kares*, that's going to be חמץ *chametz*
in a mixture. So we very conveniently interpret מחמצת *machmetzes* differently based
on how we think like the hierarchy should fall out. Okay, so
מחמצת *machmetzes* means not standard חמץ *chametz*. So the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*
that says כרת kares, *kares* we say it means a leavening agent
was part of the process and a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that says
לאו lav *lav* and we want to say no כרת kares. *kares*,
there we say it means in a mixture.
Does that assume no one says שאור se'or, *se'or* is the same
as מחמצת *machmetzes*?
Not here. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי *i hachi*
this says שאור se'or *se'or* when it wants to say שאור se'or
*se'or*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי דלאו נמי להכי הוא
דאתא *i hachi d'lav nami l'hachi hu d'asa*? If that's true, the
גמרא *Gemara* doesn't like that, you know, picking and choosing. If מחמצת
*machmetzes* means with an additional leavening agent, that's what a negative prohibition
comes to tell you is that case of a leavening agent, not
your case of תערובת ta'aroves, *ta'aroves*. אלא *ela* the גמרא *Gemara* says
fine, טעמא דרבי אליעזר מכל *ta'ama d'Rebbe Eliezer mi'kol*. Forget the word
מחמצת *machmetzes*. You're right. מחמצת *machmetzes* means this issue of a leavening
agent. How does he know to include תערובת ta'aroves, *ta'aroves*? כל kol.
מחמצת *kol machmetzes*. And the word כל kol *kol* is only in
one פסוק *pasuk* so we're safe. Okay, the word כל kol *kol*
is כל kol מחמצת לא תאכלו *kol machmetzes lo socheilu* so the
כל kol *kol* means even בתערובת betaaroves, *b'ta'aroves*. And that word you
don't have by כרת kares? *kares*. So since you don't have it
by כרת *kares* we get the idea that תערובת ta'arovet, *ta'aroves* is
a negative prohibition and not כרת *kares*. Okay, מכל *mi'kol*. The גמרא
*Gemara* says one minute, התם נמי הכתיב כל kol *hasam nami hach'siv
kol*. It says כל kol *kol* by כרת *kares* as well. כי
כל ki kol אוכל ochel, מחמצת ונכרתה *ki kol ochel machmetzes venichresa*.
So can you tell me before we read the next line in
the גמרא *Gemara* what the difference is? How come כל kol. מחמצת
לא תאכלו *kol machmetzes lo socheilu* includes תערובת ta'arovet. *ta'aroves*, but כי
כל אוכל חמץ ki kol ochel chametz ונכרתה *ki kol ochel chametz
venichresa* does not include תערובת ta'arovet *ta'aroves*?
Because it's חמץ ונכרתה *chametz venichresa* as opposed to...
No, but what is כל kol *kol* modifying? In the first case
כל kol *kol* is modifying כל kol מחמצת *kol machmetzes*. Anything that
is somehow related to חמץ *chametz* including תערובת ta'arovet, *ta'aroves*. כי כל
אוכל חמץ ki kol ochel chametz, *ki kol ochel chametz*, it's the
object is חמץ *chametz*. כל kol, *kol* is including a larger category
of people. Okay, and that's what the גמרא *Gemara* answers. ההוא מיבעי
ליה לרבות את הנשים *hahu mibayei lei l'rabos es hanashim*. That's including
more people, it's including women. So the גמרא *Gemara* says women? נשים
*nashim*? מדרב יהודה אמר רב נפקא *mi'Rav Yehuda amar Rav nafka*. We
know it from a general principle of Rav Yehuda in the name
of Rav. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב *d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*
וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *vechen tana d'vei Rebbe Yishmael* אמר קרא
*amar kra* the פסוק *pasuk* says איש או אשה ish o isha
כי ki יעשו מכל חטאת האדם *ish o isha ki ya'asu mikol
chatos ha'adam*. השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשין שבתורה *hishva haksiv isha
l'ish l'chol onshin shebaTorah*. The Torah equates men and women for all
negative prohibitions. There's never a distinction. You know, women are equally prohibited
as men. Distinctions occur in positive מצוות *mitzvos* not in negative ones.
The גמרא *Gemara* says איצטריך *itztrich*. No, you still need it. סלקא
דעתך אמינא *salka dach'tach amina* I would have thought to say הואיל
וכתיב *ho'il uchesiv* לא תאכל עליו חמץ *lo sochel alav chametz* שבעת
ימים תאכל עליו מצות *shivas yamim sochel alav matzos* כל kol שישנו
בקום אכול מצה matzah, ישנו בבל תאכל חמץ *kol sheyeshno bekum echol
matzah yeshno beval sochel chametz*. If you're commanded in מצה matzah. *matzah*
then you're commanded in חמץ *chametz*. והני נשי הואיל וליתנהו בקום אכול
מצה matzah. *vehani neshei ho'il u'leisnehu bekum echol matzah* and I would
have assumed that women are not included in מצה matzah. *matzah* דהוי
מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה *dehavei mitzvas asei shehazman grama* it's a time-bound
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. אימא בבל תאכל חמץ נמי ליתנהו הוא, I would
have assumed if they don't have a מצוה mitzvah מצה, matzah, they
don't have a prohibition of חמץ. So they would have been an
exception to the rule because it's connected to מצה. matzah. קא משמע
לן, ka mashma lan, it says כי כל אוכל חמץ ki kol
ocheil chametz, that women are also prohibited. Now I go the reverse.
והשתא דאיתרבו להו בבל תאכל חמץ, vehashta deisrabu lehu beval tochal chametz,
now that I know that women are prohibited in
חמץ, איתרבו נמי לאכילת מצה. israbu nami lachilas matzah. So I use
the link not to exclude them from חמץ, I use the link
to include them in מצה. matzah. Once I get כי כל ki
kol. tell me women are prohibited in חמץ, if they're prohibited in
חמץ, they're obligated in מצה. matzah. כדרבי אלעזר, k'rabbi elazar, דאמר רבי
אלעזר, de'amar rabbi elazar, נשים חייבות באכילת מצה דבר תורה. nashim chayavos
ba'achilas matzah dvar torah. Women are biblically obligated in
מצה, matzah. שנאמר, לא תאכל עליו חמץ שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות.
lo sochal alav chametz shivas yamim tochal alav matzos. כל שישנו בבל
תאכל חמץ, kol sheyeshno beval tochal chametz, anybody prohibited
in חמץ, ישנו באכילת מצה, yeshno ba'achilas matzah, is in the מצוה
מצה. matzah. והני נשים, vehani nashim, women, הוה נמי איתנהו בבל תאכל
חמץ, hava nami esnu beval tochal chametz, since they're prohibited in חמץ,
ישנן בקום אכול מצה, yeshnan bekum achol matzah, they're commanded in מצה.
matzah, Okay, so basically very straightforward point. מחמצת admittedly is not the
word that we're focusing on, that has to do with external leavening
agents. The word is כל. kol כל kol, מחמצת includes תערובת, ta'arovet?
but it's never in a פסוק of כרת. The time we have
the word כל kol, by כרת is כי כל ki kol אוכל
ochel, חמץ, and that is coming to include more people, coming to
include women. But by the prohibition, by the object, that is only
a negative prohibition of a תערובת, ta'arovet it is not a כרת.
According to this the structure of the הלכה halacha argument though is
that they became precipitously close to considering that women were פטורות pturos
from חמץ.
Not generally, from the one of חמץ, because of its link to
מצה. matzah? It never generalized it. It said why do you even
need to tell me not חמץ, there's a general principle? It said
this might have been an exception to the general rule because of
its link to חמץ. איש או אשה tells me women are included...
oh you mean that דרשה drasha prior to that דרשה drasha we
might have assumed that. Yeah, that's the foundation of the entire שקלא
וטריא. shakla v'tarya. Yes, prior to that דרשה. drasha.
So she was barely even in the room.
Maybe. Okay, you know, it's a question how many things do we
think are really being considered.
All right, so it's like we're saying עדת ישראל, adas yisrael, we
would be thinking of excluding נשים from the עדת ישראל?
adas yisrael? Okay, we can have that conversation another time, okay,
whether the תורה torah in general is assumed to be speaking only
to men. Like it says, אגדה, agada, I'm coming to give the
תורה torah to all of בני ישראל, bnei yisrael, היו נכונים לשלשת
ימים אל תגשו אל אשה. heyu nechonim lishloshas yamim al tigsnu el
isha. Okay?
So it's a big problem that the, or whatever it is, the
Torah's basic audience being addressed is the men, and women and children
are like, you know, in the periphery there, adjuncts. Okay, anyway. So
the גמרא says like
this: ומאי חזית דהאי כל לריבויי נשים ומפקעיה רובא, umai chazis dehai
kol leribuy nashim umafkei rova, what makes you think that the first
כל kol. where it says כרת is to include women but not
talking about תערובת, Taaroves. the כרת פסוק? אימא, why not say לריבויי
רובא, leribuy rova, that it's coming to include a תערובת, maybe that's
what the כל kol is doing even by כרת? So I already
gave you the answer to that. מסתברא, mistabra, it makes sense, קאי
באוכלים מרבי באוכלים. kai be'ochlin marbei be'ochlin. It says כי כל ki
kol אוכל, so you're talking about the eaters, so the word כל
kol includes a larger category of eaters. קאי באוכלים מרבי בנאכלים? kai
be'ochlin marbei bene'achalin? You're talking about eaters and the word כל is
to expand the objects that are being eaten? No. כל אוכל kol
ochel expands the people that are doing the eating. מתקיף לה רב
נתן אבוה דרב הונא, matkif lah rav nathan avuh d'rav huna, Rav
Nathan the father of Rav Huna asks a fine question. ובכל היכא
דקאי באוכלים לא מרבי בנאכלים? uvechol heicha dekai be'ochlin lo marbei bene'achalin?
Are you telling me anytime we're talking about eaters, we're not going
to expand the objects being eaten?
והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, כי כל אוכל חלב,
ki kol ochel chelev, anybody who eats חלב. chelev. So the כל
is modifying the word אוכל, the eaters. And what do we learn
from this? מן הבהמה אשר יקריב, min habeheima asher yakriv, from the
animal that you bring as a קרבן. korban. So here's the דרשה:
drasha: אין לי אלא חלב תמימים, ein li ela chelev tmimim, I
only know חלב chelev of unblemished
animals, שראוי ליקרב, sheraui l'ikarev, that you can bring as a sacrifice,
because it says אשר יקריב ממנו קרבן להשם. asher yakriv mimenu korban
lashem. חלב בעלי מומין מנין? chelev ba'alei mumin minayin? How do I
know חלב chelev of animals with blemishes? How do I know
אשר יקריב asher yakriv is not talking about the specific animal but
talking about the species of animal? So therefore even an animal with
a blemish. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, מן הבהמה. min habeheima. So from
the בהמה, beheima, I don't see, I have to tell you I
don't exactly get what the דרשה drasha is. Okay, I don't see
where מן הבהמה min habeheima is coming to include the, is coming
to include anything in the category. I guess you don't read the
end of the פסוק, you don't read אשר יקריב, asher yakriv, you
just stop at the word מן הבהמה. min habeheima. Okay, anyway. חלב
חולין מנין? chelev chullin minayin? Fine, but maybe even that's limited to
something that's been sanctified, that was more in the category. How do
I know completely unsanctified animals? תלמוד לומר, כי כל. Talmud lomar ki
kol. Okay, but anyway the point is we get it from the
word כל. But כל is expanding on the word אוכל, eaters, not
on the animal. So you see a word כל can expand the
category of objects, not just the category of people. The גמרא says
והכא דקאי באוכלין, ve-hacha de-kai be-ochlin, it's talking about the people that
are eaters, וקא מרבה נאכלין, ve-ka marbeh ne'echalin, and the word כל
expands the objects that are being eaten. So גמרא says, okay look.
התם דליכא אוכלין, hatam de-leika ochlin, there we can't, the word כל,
there's nothing to include in the people in the category of eaters.
Obviously it includes everybody. So if you have nothing to do with
the word, so מרבה נאכלין, marbeh ne'echalin, so you'll use it to
include, to expand the objects of things that are being eaten. הכא
דאיכא אוכלין, hacha de-ika ochlin, here there is a category of eaters
that we have to include, women. לא שבקינן לאוכלין, lo shavkinan le-ochlin,
we're not going to ignore expanding the natural category of eaters, which
is what it's modifying and we need to include women, ומרבינן נאכלין
u-marbinan ne'echalin and come to include, expand the objects and to include
תערובת חמץ.
Taaroves Chametz, Why does he make the same argument by the חלב?
chelev? How do you know it includes women?
No, because we know women are prohibited on all negative prohibitions. The
only reason that we would have, we thought to exclude them here
was because of the link to מצה. Okay, obviously we always assume
women are included, but here maybe they would have been excluded because
of the link to מצה. We needed the פסוק to insist that
they were included. Okay, that's what I was telling you before, we
never seriously excluded women from all things; the הוה אמינא hava amina
was just to say that they could eat חמץ.
And once,
does קטנים ketanim go with that and עבדים avadim with the women?
Well, I'm not going to talk about קטנים, ketanim, קטנים ketanim are
not חייב במצוות, chayav be-mitzvot, עבדים avadim are like women. Anyway, yes.
So let's move on. So now the גמרא says like this, what
we have is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learns from כל that
there's a prohibition of תערובת חמץ, and the חכמים Chachamim say, and
the חכמים Chachamim say there's not even a biblical prohibition. I said
this is crazy, again just to remind you, who needs a special
פסוק? It's איסור בתערובת. issur be-ta'arovet. So again, two basic answers. One
is it's unique to the idea of לחם, lechem, and the other
is it's small proportions and therefore even though you can taste it,
according to the חכמים Chachamim you do not get, you do not
get כרת, you do not get a לאו lav even, even though
it can be tasted, and according to רבי אליעזר you get a
לאו lav. but you do not get כרת. Okay. So the גמרא
says like this, וכי תימא, ve-chi teima, where were we? אלא לרבנן
דלית להו עירובא כל לא דרשי. ela le-rabbanan de-leit lehu eiruva kol
lo darshi.
So the rabbis who don't have this idea of תערובת, they don't
feel the word כל is coming to include תערובת. אלא נשים מנא
להו? ela nashim mana lehu?
So then if they don't use the word כל, how do they
say that women are prohibited to eat חמץ? We learned that also
from the word כל, כל
אוכל. kol ocheil. כל לא דרשי, kol lo darshi, you're right, they
don't do anything with the word כל. כי כל דרשי. ki kol
darshi. But the double emphasis, כי כל ki kol. אוכל חמץ, that
they'll give some weight to and that they'll use to include women.
Okay. ורבי אליעזר אימא כל לרבות את הנשים כי כל לרבות
את העירובא. ve-Rabbi Eliezer eima kol lerabot et ha-nashim ki kol lerabot
et ha-eiruva. Okay, now that you're saying the extra word כי ki
comes to do something, has more punch, so maybe for רבי אליעזר
the כי כל ki kol should tell you, we've already included women
by the כל אוכל ונכרתה, kol ocheil ve-nichretah, maybe the כי ki,
should tell us that תערובת you get כרת. וכי תימא כי כל
לרבי אליעזר לא דריש, ve-chi teima ki kol le-Rabbi Eliezer lo darish,
and if you say רבי אליעזר doesn't make anything from the extra
word כי, כל ki kol and כי כל is all the same.
והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Beraita, שאור בל תקטירו. se'or
bal taktiro. So there's the, the תורה Torah says that you cannot
burn up שאור, se'or. right, חמץ or שאור se'or on the
מזבח. mizbeiach. כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא
תקטירו ממנו
אשה לה'.
ki kol se'or ve-chol devash lo
taktiro mimenu isheh l'Hashem.
ועל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. ve-al ha-mizbeiach lo ya'alu le-rei'ach nicho'ach.
Okay, so you can't, so okay, so it says כי כל שאור.
ki kol se'or. So how much שאור do you have to burn
in order to transgress? שאור בל תקטירו. se'or bal taktiro. אין לי
אלא כולו, ein li ela kulo, I only know the full amount.
Full amount might mean a full handbreath or a full כזית. kezayit.
ומקצתו מנין, u-miktzato minayin, less than the standard full amount, how do
I know you transgress? תלמוד לומר כל, Talmud lomar kol, any שאור.
עירובו מנין, eiruvo minayin, how do I know even if it's mixed
up with other stuff, like you have a mixture of שאור and
מצה, you know from a מנחה mincha which is made of מצה?
How do I know you transgress? Again, that we need a פסוק
for תערובת, this is interesting. תלמוד לומר כי כל. Okay, so they're
doubling with כי כל. מאן שמעת ליה דדריש כל? man shamat lei
de-darish kol? Who do we know is the normal one that says,
"Oh, כל is coming to include, you know, more objects"? רבי אליעזר.
דקא
דרשי כי כל, de-ka darshi ki kol, and by the double כי
כל he gets א, aleph, less than the requisite amount, and ב,
בתערובת. So you see כי כל has some punch for him. So
why doesn't he use that to tell me that you get כרת
for תערובת? So the גמרא says קשיא. kashya. All right, that's a
problem. So anyway, you know, at a certain point it's like, okay,
are we done with the דרשות drashot yet? Fine. So anyway, but
what we have is, just to remind us, and I think we'll
end here cause next it gets into a big new discussion so
we'll end a few minutes early. But the משנה contains two major
categories: חמץ that's a real food בתערובת, which is probably 90 percent
of the stuff we don't eat on חמץ, on פסח, Pesach, stuff
that has some תערובת in
it on פסח. Pesach. And the other one is נוקשה, which is
the whole stuff about going to your medicine cabinets and whatnot. Okay,
and things that are not really foods or they're... Are edible but
they haven't fully fermented. Those are the two categories. רבי מאיר and
clearly has and maybe even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda clearly has this
category of נוקשה. רבי אליעזר clearly has this category of תערובת. Is
there one that holds both is not clear. But what we also
found out is that not everybody agrees. Our משנה is taught סתם.
stam. You would have read our משנה, you would have assumed it
would be without debate. But what we actually find out is that
תערובת חמץ, which for us should have been so obviously אסור, assur,
and maybe even get כרת, according to the חכמים Chachamim there's no
prohibition, maybe there's a חצי שיעור chatzi shiur prohibition, but there's no
lashes for it, no self-standing prohibition, no לאו. lav It could still
be a חצי שיעור chatzi shiur issue, okay, because of ביטול, bittul,
whatever, you still have little traces of חמץ that you're eating. Okay,
and according to רבי אליעזר there's לאו and not כרת. And again,
why is it not כרת? As I said, it could be a
question either that there's not enough of it, you don't have a
כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, kezayis bichdei achilas pras, so it's in small
proportions, or number two, perhaps something unique about the identity of חמץ
and לחם lechem and so on, which means that once it's בתערובת,
it can no longer be considered paradigm חמץ, even if it has
a high degree of proportions and so on. So we will continue
with this and with related discussions tomorrow on שבת. Shabbat. Peace out.